Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Milwaukee Urban Observatory Records, 1965-1983
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Milwaukee Urban Observatory Records, 1965-1983
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Milwaukee Urban Observatory
UWM Archival Collection 73
3.2 cubic ft. (4 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
The Milwaukee Urban Observatory (MUO) was a research center for urban studies. The records contain correspondence, memos, and minutes about the routine operations of the MUO as well as a variety of reports and research publications detailing urban problems and possible solutions. A sampling of topics included in these reports are freeway impact, taxes, elderly housing, property values, the university's impact on the surrounding community, and racial divisions. Also included are copies of the Urban Observer, a publication of the MUO, and extensive correspondence between Milwaukee Mayor Henry Maier's office and the MUO.
The Urban Observatory idea was designed to foster a partnership for research between the academic community and metropolitan government officials. This idea was first proposed by Bob Wood of MIT in 1962 and received significant backing from Milwaukee Mayor Henry Maier while he was president of the National League of Cities in 1965. This effort culminated in Milwaukee being one of the six pilot cities for the project in 1969. The MUO operates under the National League of Cities and supported primarily by the cooperative funds of UWM, UW-Extension, City of Milwaukee, and the United States Departments of Housing and Urban Development and Health, Education, and Welfare. The MUO ceased operations after 1983.
The files are organized alphabetically by subject, then chronologically.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
Milwaukee (Wis.). Mayor: Records of the Henry W. Maier Administration Milwaukee Series 44 Milwaukee Tape 1235A
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown individual transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. Additional reports held by the Employment and Training Institute were transferred to the Archives as part of accession 2016-036 in February 2017
Contents List
- Access Study, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Allocation of State Aids and Shared Taxes in Wisconsin, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Brochures, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Business Study, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Cable TV Project
  - Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft Proposals, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Census Data Project, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Census Facts: Milwaukee Areas and Neighborhoods, 1970-1980 Statistics Compared, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Census Update, City of Milwaukee, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Chapter 220 Research Project, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Citizen Attitude Survey, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Citizen Participation Models, CR-SDC, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Citizen Participation Study, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Commercial Insurance: Selected Areas in the City of Milwaukee, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Committee on Discipline and Human Relations, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Communications Technology Project, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Conference, School Desegregation, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Co-op Housing Study, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Council of Observers, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Current Trends in Wisconsin Population Conference, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Decision Making in Municipal Development Programs and Federal Grants-In-Aid, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- D ecision Making on Capitol Programs, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Elderly Housing Report, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Engineering Geology in the Milwaukee Area, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Evaluation for a Community Wide System of Primary Health Care, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Evaluations, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Exclusionary Zoning Project, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Faculty-Community Connection, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Fifth Year Research Projects, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- First Offender Project, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Fiscal, Legal, and Social Implications of Merging the Milwaukee Mental Health Center as Part of the Milwaukee County Hospital Complex, Final Report, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Freeway Impact Study, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Freeway Impact Study
  - Phase I, Final Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Phase II, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Full Count 1980 Information: Greater Milwaukee Area Including City of Milwaukee Neighborhoods and 1970-1980 Percentages, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Functions and Activities, 1970-1983 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Getting it Together in Milwaukee: From Census Data to Fact Book in Thirteen Steps or More, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Greater Milwaukee 1970-1980 Census Data, by Race and Spanish Origin, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Greater Milwaukee Urban Caucus, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Greenleigh Associates Evaluation, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Health Needs of the Elderly, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- History and Formation, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Housing Policies Manuscript, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Housing Policies Study, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Housing Policies Study, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Housing Policies Study, Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Immigration and Education in Milwaukee Public Schools, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Impact of Housing on the University in Milwaukee East Side and Shorewood, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Impact of the School of Nursing's Outreach Activities on the Greater Milwaukee Metropolitan Community, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Impact of the University on Housing, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Impact of the University on Housing, Final Report, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Information Systems Project, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Information on Milwaukee Urban Observatory, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Inter-Institutional Committee, Minutes, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Labor Force Involvement of Milwaukee's Working Women: Focus on Milwaukee's Racial Gap, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Letters of Support for Proposed 1980 Metropolitan Milwaukee Fact Book, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Letters to Mayor Maier, 1970, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Local Involvement, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Manpower Policies Study, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Match-Title I, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Mayor's Task Forces, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Metropolitan Milwaukee Fact Book: 1970, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Metropolitan Milwaukee Fact Book
  - Legal Problems, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Progress Reports, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Funding, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Metropolitan Milwaukee Higher Education Inter-Institutional Committee on Title I, Response to Establish Urban Observatory, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- The Milwaukee Observer, 1972-1983 (Box 2, Folder 26-30)
- Minority Business Development Program, Cost Benefit Analysis, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Model Cities, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Municipal Finance Study, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Municipal Ordinances Recodification Project, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- National Academy of Public Administration Evaluation, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- National League of Cities
  - Contract, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Contract Amendments 1-22, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 37-39)
  - Contract Termination, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Quarterly Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Neighborhood Approval Technical Task Force, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Neighborhood Design and Development, General Correspondence and Project Proposals, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Observer Readership Survey, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Ombudsman, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Open Enrollment in Milwaukee, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Physical Facilities for Child Care and Educational Environments, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Planning Conference on the Ethics of Robotics and Artificial Intelligence Research, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Planning for Juvenile Programs in Suburban Areas, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Policy Alternatives for Development of Milwaukee's North Harbor Tract, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Profile of the SMSA (Standard Metropolitan Statistical Area), Correspondence and Report, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Progress Reports, 1969-1982 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- Public Technology Incorporated (PTI) and The Urban Technology System (UTS), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Publication Lists, 1970-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Regional Economic Analysis, Correspondence and General, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Regional Employment Migration Study, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Residential Search Patterns of Black Urban Households, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Revenue Sharing, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Riverwest Study, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- School Desegregation Planning, Milwaukee, 1976: Chronology, Plans, and Participants, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Sewer Project, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Social Indicators
  - Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - First and Second Year Work Program, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Reports, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Social Indicators II, Data Sheets--Originals, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- A Social Report for Milwaukee: Trends and Indicators, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Stimulating Urban Economic Development, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Strengths in the Black Community, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Summary Report for the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development on the Milwaukee Urban Observatory September 20, 1969 - June 30, 1974, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Survey, Latin Community, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Tax Control Forum, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Technical Advisory Council, 1969-1975 (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
- Technical Advisory Council, Health and Social Change, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Urban Committee, 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 38-41)
- Urban Committee, NASA Program, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Urban Committee, Press Conferences, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Urban Information Center, 1971-1983 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Urban Observatory Conferences, 1965, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 45-46)
- Usage, 1973-1982 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- What's New in Financing for Local Governments, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- William P. Irwin, Papers, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Work Program, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)